I would like to discuss with
you, using some small artificial examples,
the different properties that
we have seen in
the context of liveness, and
in particular look at combinations.
So when can this property and that
property occur at the same time or not?
First, let's look at this simple example.
What do we have there?
Simply a small Petri net
with two places and two transitions.
We can just fire this
a little bit, and we see:
Not that much can happen there.
In the initial situation,
only t1 can fire.
That would move the token here.
And after that, only t2 can fire.
That would move the token up here.
These are all possibilities.
Of course, this can go on and on, but
other processes than these are not possible at all.
What does this say about this Petri net?
Is it, for example, weakly alive?
There was the criterion
that every transition that
occurs in the Petri net (in the case
t1 and t2) can actually fire at some point.
That is, from the start
marking, a marking is reachable
in which the respective t is activated.
We have just seen that we can
fire t1 and t2 in any case, and
relatively quickly: t1 in the first
step, t2 in the second step.
There are no other transitions at all.
So this Petri net will be weakly lively.
What about strong liveness?
For this, the stronger statement must
hold that for each transition (in which
case again to be checked separately
for t1 and t2), and no matter
how long the Petri net has
been executed (and evolved into some
marking), it is still possible from there
to fire the respective t at some time.
If necessary after further steps.
In this example, it is like this.
We have seen that
t1, t2 is constantly fireable.
And there is also no development
of the Petri net into a
situation, from which afterwards never
again t1 or t2 is fireable.
So this will also be true.
Obviously, the Petri net
is not deadlocked either.
Because no matter how we
proceed, we always get further.
There is no situation that is reachable
from which no single transition is fireable.
So here we would expect all
three interesting properties we have seen
to apply: weakly alive,
strongly alive, and deadlock-free.
Can we also verify
this on the reachability graph?
We might want to draw that for a moment.
We know that it will have only two nodes.
We have just seen that there are
actually only two constellations
for this Petri net.
There is the start marking.
This is the one we see right now.
I always take the numbering
s1, s2 as the place
order here (also
in the following examples).
So how the places are numbered
is how I take them when
I use the tuple notation.
Therefore I can write here (1,0)
as the marking, which is currently seen.
If I were to take this one
step here, down here, that's a t1
step down here, and there's the marking (0,1).
Of course, I'll come back with
t2, so I'll still write t1 and
t2 here at the transitions, and also mark
that this is the start marking up here.
So what we see
here is the reachability graph.
We can see from this, too,
that the Petri net is weakly lively.
Because for that to happen, every transition just
has to occur somewhere in the reachability graph.
This is obviously the case
here for both t1 and t2.
We can also read
from this finite reachability graph
that the Petri net is strongly alive.
For no matter where we are (whether here or
here), it is always possible to execute t1 after possibly
further steps, as well as to
execute t2 again at some point.
In that case, either
directly or after a step.
This system is obviously also deadlock-free,
because there are no dead ends.
There is no node in the reachability graph
from which it would not go on at all.
Of course, we already know that:
The system has to be deadlock-free
because it is very much alive.
Because of one of the
statements on a slide, that a
Petri net, which is strongly alive,
is always also weakly alive and deadlock-free.
That would be our first example.
Let's look at another example that just
doesn't exactly satisfy all of those three properties.
We will now see examples that each
have at most some of these properties.
What about this Petri net?
It doesn't have all three
of the properties we just saw.
Which one does it not have?
That can be actually
only the strong liveliness.
Because if it had that, it
would also have the other two.
Then it would not be true that
it does not have all three properties.
So, how can this Petri net behave?
First, of course, it
can execute t1 at the
beginning, any number
of times, including never.
Then, at some point, it could execute t2.
Then the token would be over here.
Then it would still be possible
to execute t3 any number of times.
In particular, this Petri
net is obviously deadlock-free.
Even back here, we can still
execute t3 any number of times.
So we can already
state that it is deadlock-free.
Of course, we can again convince
ourselves of this by the reachability graph.
So let's set it up.
How many markings are there
here that are relevant?
Again, exactly two.
We have just seen that above.
There's the marking where the one token
that exists in the system is on s1.
That would be this start marking (1,0).
And there's the other marking where
the token has migrated to s2.
What are the transitions?
First of all, this is the start marking.
There is the t1 transition
from the start marking to itself.
There is the t2 transition from
the start marking to the other.
That's right where this
very token moves across.
That would be t2.
And then there's a transition out of
the second marking with t3 to itself, so
that can then still
be executed again and again.
So this transition in the graph.
Deadlock-free:
There's no node from
which it can't continue.
That's true.
What's also true, that's
the interesting observation here:
This Petri net is weakly alive.
Why is that?
Because every transition occurs
in the reachability graph.
There is no transition
that can never be fired.
From the start marking
at least one marking is
reachable for each transition, from
which this transition is fireable.
But this Petri net is not strongly alive.
What this example also gives
us is that while weak liveness
and non-deadlocking follow
from strong liveness, not
every deadlock-free and weakly lively
Petri net is also strongly lively.
This one is not.
How can we convince ourselves of this?
What would have to
be true for strong liveness?
Let's think back to the definition.
Strong liveness would mean:
For every transition t and every
marking m reachable from the start marking m0,
there must be a marking m' reachable
from m in which t is activated.
If we say that this Petri net
is not strongly alive, then we must ask
for which t this statement is not true.
There the answer is twofold.
Namely, the statement is not
true for either t1 or t2.
However, it is sufficient to specify a t.
We can simply restrict ourselves
to t1 for the time being.
Going back to the definition:
What do we have here?
This is our m0, and we consider t1.
Then for strong liveness it would have to
be true that for every marking m reachable from
m0, for example for this one, it
must hold that there is a successor
marking (or the current marking itself),
so that t1 is fireable from there.
But in fact t1 is
never fireable again from here.
Thus, by definition, this Petri
net is just not strongly alive.
Because there is a node
in the reachability graph (namely
this one) from which, no matter how hard
we try, we will never fire t1 again.
The same explanation would have
been true for t2 as well.
So deadlock-free, weakly alive,
but not strongly alive.
Let's look at one more example, this one.
What can happen here?
We have this token up here.
On the one hand, it can constantly move
here by means of t1, so to speak.
So actually the marking
doesn't change at all,
because firing t1 leads back
to exactly the same marking.
Or we can try to fire t2.
However, that won't work, because t2
would need a token from here
(which is present) as well
as a token from here.
This actually means:
If we paint the reachability graph here,
it is very simple and very small.
In fact, there is only this
one marking here, the start marking.
Namely, one token on s1 and none on s2.
This is the start marking.
And it is such that you can fire t1, but
then you also end up
only at this start marking.
That is:
What you can see here on
the right is the entire accessibility graph.
You can then also
see how the properties are.
Is this Petri net weakly alive?
No, it is not, because
you can never fire t2.
Because there is no edge with
t2 label in the whole reachability graph.
So in fact it is not weakly lively.
It can't be strongly alive
with it either, of course.
We already know that, because any strongly
alive Petri net would be weakly alive.
So not weakly alive,
not strongly alive, but deadlock-free.
The fact that s2 prevents us from t2, so
to speak, and therefore t2 can never be executed,
does not mean that the
Petri net would have a deadlock.
After all, we can
at least always execute t1.
Or to put it another way:
In the reachability graph we see
here, there is no node
from which it cannot continue.
There is only one node anyway.
And from that one it goes
on, even if always only to itself.
That captures this combination.
What other combinations would be conceivable
between our three properties and their negations?
Let's look at this example.
What do we expect there?
There is again this token, which can be
used as often as desired to fire t1.
And it can be used
exactly once to fire t2.
And when that happens,
then we have deadlocking.
So this is already
not going to be deadlock-free.
Because we have a
clearly recognizable situation here,
where no transition can be fired anymore.
So we can already state that
this Petri net contains a deadlock.
Although not in the start
situation, but a deadlock is attainable.
Then we also know:
This cannot be strongly alive.
Again from the observation that any strongly
alive Petri net would be deadlock free.
Now the question would be whether
it is at least weakly alive.
We have just seen that
yes, every transition can be executed
at least once, in
some sequence each time.
If we again refer
to the reachability graph
and want to use that, then we
know here that there are two nodes.
There is again the start marking (1,0).
From there, we can get back
to the same marking with t1, or
to the other marking with t2.
Namely, nothing on s1, but a token on s2.
And also here we can see:
Obviously, this system is
at least weakly alive.
Because every transition
drawn in the Petri
net, both t1 and t2,
occurs in the reachability graph.
If you have now followed
the combinations, and given that weak
liveness and non-deadlocking follow
from strong liveness (and
so we cannot present
all eight combinations that would
respectively result from alternations of
"contains" versus "contains no deadlock",
is "strongly lively" versus "not
strongly lively", is "weakly lively"
versus "not weakly lively"), then only
one combination should now be possible.
And this is represented
by this example here.
What do we have here?
A very strange Petri net.
It is not even connected.
There are somehow two components here.
But that's not mathematically forbidden.
It's a valid Petri net.
What is valid about this Petri net?
What can happen here?
We can execute t1 exactly once.
Then we have reached a
new marking where nothing can happen.
So what does the
reachability graph look like?
Of course, it is
finite again and very small.
It has two markings.
Each marking consists now of a triple, because
we have the three places s1, s2, s3.
That means, the start marking,
which we draw here on
the left, has this form: one token on
s1 and no tokens on s2 and s3.
Then we can fire t1.
That leads to a new marking, which
is the marking where there is nothing on
s1, one token on s2 and nothing on s3.
And that's it.
From this marking, we had
just seen, you can't do anything.
Neither fire t1 nor fire t2.
Then this Petri net has what properties?
It is not weakly alive.
Why is that?
Because the transition t2
never comes to pass.
In the whole reachability graph, t2 does
not occur as a label of any transition.
Therefore: not weakly alive.
Logically, not strongly alive either.
This follows, among other things, from the
fact that it is not weakly alive.
And what about deadlocking?
The system is not deadlock-free either.
Because in the situation we have
seen, we have reached an entrapment.
It contains an entrapment.
So that's still the last property (of
the three properties we're looking at) that's here.
This is exactly the combination that we
didn't have before in the other examples.
So now we have seen five
examples here and we can classify them.
For the three considered
properties, one can show by
such a Venn diagram,
which possibilities/overlaps/combinations
there are.
This is supposed to indicate quantities.
So there are all possible Petri
nets, that is the outer blue set.
Inside there are subclasses.
There are weakly alive nets,
deadlock-free nets, strongly alive nets.
These are all strict subsets of
the set of all Petri nets.
Because there are also Petri nets that
don't have any of those three properties.
If we go back to this last Petri net:
This is not weakly alive,
not strongly alive, and not deadlock-free.
That is, that would live
somewhere here in this depiction.
This is a Petri net,
but it has none of these
three interesting
or desirable properties.
Also, we know that it is true
that any net that is strongly
alive is also non-deadlocked and weakly alive.
This is represented by the fact
that this is a (strict) subset
of the average of
deadlock-free and weakly alive nets.
You can tell that this is a strict
subset by the fact that there are also Petri
nets that are alive here, so they're deadlock-free
and weakly alive, but they're not strongly alive.
And we saw an example of that as well.
That would have been this example.
No, it wouldn't.
This example would be such an
example that is uninhibited and
weakly alive, but not strongly alive.
This example would live at
this point in this Venn diagram.
Also for all other
somehow interesting positions here we
find an example in each case
under the Petri nets just seen.
So for example a net, which is free
of deadlock, but is neither strongly, nor weakly alive.
Or a net which is weakly
alive, but neither strongly alive, nor deadlock-free.
This justifies that this set
diagram, which is shown
here, is really true.